Guide to the Welsh Nationality Room Committee Collection, 1931-2011 UA.40.24
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Welsh Nationality Room Committee Collection
1931-2011
2001-2008
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program. Welsh Nationality Room Committee
UA.40.24
2.9 Linear Feet (8 boxes)
The Welsh Nationality Room Committee Collection is a compilation of correspondence, meeting minutes, financial reports, various print and non-print media, draft texts, reference materials, and blueprints used by committee members from, and pertaining to, the Welsh Nationality Room at the University of Pittsburgh's Cathedral of Learning. The bulk of the materials are from 2001 to 2008.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into seven series:
Series I. Welsh Nationality Room Committee Correspondence
Series II. Nationality Room Program Correspondence
Series III. Meeting Minutes, Finance Reports and Contributors
Series IV. Dedication Day Documents
Series V. Drafts, Texts, and Photographic Reference Materials
Series VI. Print and Non-Print Media
Series VII. Architectural Renderings
Related Material
The Welsh Nationality Room is one of 28 Nationality Rooms located in the Cathedral of Learning. Records for some of the other rooms are housed at the Archive & Special Collections ASC facility.
History
In 2001 the St. David's Society of Pittsburgh approached the University of Pittsburgh's Nationality Rooms Program about the prospect of creating a Welsh Nationality Classroom. The Welsh Room Committee was established shortly thereafter, with the St. David's Society taking on the role of the committee. Dale Richards and John (Jack) Owens were appointed committee chairs. Information and plans about the proposed Welsh Nationality Room were conveyed via St. David's Society newsletters and meeting minutes.
After considering designs for a Welsh manor house, castle, and a farmhouse, the committee decided upon an 18th-century Non-Conformist chapel. Rural chapels, such as the Pen-rhiw Chapel in Cardiff, Wales (after which the Welsh Nationality Room is modeled), were considered to be centers of village social life, education, and worship. The Welsh Nationality Room Committee chose The Design Alliance architecture firm to draw up plans for the Welsh room.
Many fundraising events were sponsored by the St. David's Society -- most notably, the annual Gymanfa Ganu, or Welsh singing festivals. With the help of several corporate sponsors, including an appointment of Bob Evans as honorary chairman, the Welsh Nationality Room Committee was able to raise the entirety of their funds by 2007. Construction began in November 2007 and was completed in April 2008.
Features of the Welsh Nationality Room include a pulpit, deacon's benches, a long-case clock, a communion table, box pew seating, and milk paint on the walls. The Welsh room was dedicated on June 1, 2008 - the least amount of time taken from conception to completion for any Nationality Classroom. The Welsh Nationality Room Committee remains active with the Nationality Rooms Program, funding study-abroad scholarships and participating in open house cultural events at the Cathedral of Learning.
Previous Citation
Welsh Nationality Room Committee Collection, 1931-2011, UA.40.24, University Archives, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Scope and Content Notes
The Welsh Nationality Room Collection comprises materials acquired by the Nationality Rooms Program from c. 1931 through 2011, though the bulk of the items are dated 2001-2008. Most of the materials in this collection pertain to the fundraising for and construction of the Welsh Nationality Room at the Cathedral of Learning. This collection includes correspondence, newsletters, meeting minutes, financial reports, fundraising media, text drafts, photographs, print and non-print media, reference materials, and blueprints.
Acquisition Information
The materials in the Welsh Nationality Room Committee Collection were acquired by the Nationality Rooms Program at the University of Pittsburgh from 2001 through 2011. The collection was transferred to the University Archives in 2012.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions, except Box 2, Folder 13: Nationality Rooms Program General Correspondence 2005-2006.
Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Classrooms -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; University of Pittsburgh; Photographs; Minutes (Administrative records); Financial records; Correspondence; Clippings (Information artifacts); Architectural drawings (Visual works); Welsh -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Welsh Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program; Nationality Rooms (Cathedral of Learning, Pittsburgh, Pa.); University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program. Welsh Nationality Room Committee; Welsh Classroom (Cathedral of Learning, Pittsburgh, Pa.)
- Welsh Nationality Room Committee Correspondence, 2001-2011; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains general correspondences of the Welsh Nationality Room Committee and the St. David's Society. Included are: advertisements and fundraising letters; periodic newsletters and brochures distrubuted by the St. David's Society; historical notes; project manuals; bids, re-bids, and bid analyses pertaining to the plans for Welsh room; and the preliminary sketches and architectural renderings submitted by the Design Alliance Architectural Firm for the design of the Welsh Nationality Room.
  - WNRC General Correspondence
    - Welsh Nationality Room Committee General Correspondence, 2001-2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Welsh Nationality Room Project Manual, November 2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Welsh Nationality Room Bid Manual, January 2007 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Welsh Nationality Room Re-Bid Manual, April 2007 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Welsh Nationality Room Bid Analyses, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Newsletters, Brochures and Preliminary Sketches
    - St. David's Society Newsletters, 2001-2011 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - St. David's Society of Pittsburgh Brochures, c. 2004 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Welsh Nationality Room Sketches and Plans, 2002-2009 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Nationality Rooms Program General Correspondence, II.
  This series houses correspondence accumulated by the Nationality Rooms Program and the Welsh Nationality Room Committee throughout the planning and construction of the Welsh Nationality Room located in the Cathedral of Learning at the University of Pittsburgh. Included are: letters from members of the Pittsburgh Welsh community to Ruth Crawfor Mitchell (director of the Nationality Rooms Program from 1926-1956); file materials; university communications; handwritten notes from notable figures involved with the Welsh Nationality Room Committee; early design proposals; and other notes pertaining to the dedication of the Welsh Room.
  Folder 10 features a signed letter from former Member of Parliament (MP), Martyn Jones. Jones, a British Labour Party politician and former Chairman of the Welsh Affairs Committee, served as MP for the Clwyd South constituency of the House of Commons from 1987 until his retirement at the 2010 general election.
  - Nationality Rooms Program Pre-Committee Welsh Files, 1931-1984 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Nationality Rooms Program General Correspondence, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Nationality Rooms Program General Correspondence, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Nationality Rooms Program General Correspondence, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Nationality Rooms Program General Correspondence, 2005-2006 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Access Restrictions
    Restricted due to personal content
  - Nationality Rooms Program General Correspondence, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Nationality Rooms Program General Correspondence, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Nationality Rooms Program General Correspondence, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Nationality Rooms Program General Correspondence, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Nationality Rooms Program General Correspondence, 2009-2011 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Nationality Rooms Program General Correspondence, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Personal Correspondence, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Meeting Minutes, Finance Reports and Contributors, III.
  This series contains the meeting minutes of the St. David's Society of Pittsburgh, as well as minutes from construction planning meetings between the Design Alliance architecture firm, St. David's Society members, the University of Pittsburgh architects, Nationality Rooms Program staff, and various other vendors including Poerio Construction, Clugsten Cabinetry, and Lisanti Painting. Also included in the series are the monthly financial summary reports generated by the University of Pittsburgh accounting system. A draft copy of the donor book for the Welsh Nationality Room concludes the series.
  - St. David's Society Meetings, 2002-2008 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Construction Meeting Minutes, 2003-2009 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Financial Reports, 2001-2011 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    scope
  - Donor Book Draft, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Dedication Day Documents, 2008; IV.
  This series contains materials pertaining to the dedication day ceremony of the Welsh Nationality Room on June 1, 2008. Included are the formal planning and operational materials generated by the Nationality Rooms Program for the dedication ceremony; printed invitations and sample RSVPs; guest lists and address worksheets of the invitees; copies of the official program created for the dedication day ceremony, as well as the final version of the Welsh Nationality Room booklet.
  - Dedication Day Guest List, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Dedication Day Sample Invitations, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Dedication Programs, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Dedication Day Materials, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Welsh Nationality Room Booklets, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Nationality Rooms Program Planning and Operational Materials, 2007-2008 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Nationality Rooms Program Planning and Operational Materials, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Drafts, Texts, and Photographic Reference Materials, V.
  This series primarily consists of textual and photographic reference materials utilized by members of the St. David's Society, as well as the Nationality Rooms Program staff, for the planning and design of the Welsh Nationality Room. Textual reference documents include information on Welsh genealogy, Welsh pronunciations, prominent Welsh-Americans, Welsh traditions, and Welsh symbols and icons. Photographic reference materials include photos taken during trips to Wales, graphics of Welsh symbols and icons, and maps; photographs of the Welsh Nationality Room can also be found in the series. Also included are reference publications and newsletters of various Welsh societies throughout the United States. The remainder of the series includes draft versions of the Welsh Nationality Room booklet, the dedication day program, and other textual materials related to the Welsh Nationality Room.
  - Welsh Nationality Room Booklet Drafts, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Other Text Drafts, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Textual Reference Materials, 2004-2008 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Photographs, 2000-2008 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Photographic Reference Materials, 2007-2008 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Reference Publications, 1945-1950 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Reference Publications, 1998-2001 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Reference Publications, 2003-2005 (Box 5, Folder 39)
- Print and Non-Print Media, VI.
  This series consists of four folders which contain print and non-print media releases, as well as fundraising advertisements and newspaper articles pertaining to the Welsh Nationality Room. Topics covered include: preliminary and final plans; construction progress; fundraising efforts and events; leadership; and dedication of the Welsh room. The series also includes an audio CD of Welsh tenor Kenneth Davies; two CDs of photographs depicting the construction and progress of the Welsh room; and information pertaining to notable fundraising events, including several Gymanfa Ganus-Welsh Hymnal Festivals and a Dylan Thomas Poetry reading in 2003.
  - Newspaper Articles, 1999-2009 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Fundraising Media, 2001-2009 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Media Releases, 2001-2008 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Non-print Media, 2005-2008 (Box 6, Folder 43)
- Architectural Renderings, 2006-2007; VII.
  This series houses two complete rolls of blueprints created by the Design Alliance Architects for the Welsh Nationality Room. The first is dated November 27, 2006, with the subsequent updated version of January 9, 2007.
  - Welsh Nationality Room Blueprints, November 2006 (Box 7)
  - Welsh Nationality Room Blueprints, January 2007 (Box 8)